Namo Buddha Shakyamuni.
Nam Mô Phật Bổn Sư Thích Ca Mâu Ni Kính
Dear fellow practitioners, today we
thưa các quý đạo hữu hôm nay chúng ta
address a question regarding the
đến với câu hỏi của chúng ta đó là câu
benefits of practicing the correct order within the Dharma
lợi ích thực hành đúng thứ lớp tại đạo
center.
tràng
The question is as follows: A Buddhist in the Dharma center, who is
câu hỏi như sau phật tử trong đạo tràng
not a member of the leadership committee and does not wish to be one,
không phải là ban cán sự cũng không chịu
encourages other
làm ban cán sự nhưng hay sách tấn các
Buddhists in the center in ways that are not in accordance with
phật tử trong đạo tràng không đúng với
their duties. Everyone knows that
bổn phận của mình mọi người cũng biết là
asking such questions is wrong, but due to
hỏi như thế không đúng nhưng vì có việc
embarrassment, the group is hesitant to ask and instead
ngại hỏi nên nhóm ngại hỏi lên tổ ngài
asks the leadership committee. Therefore, they ask
hỏi ban cán sự ban lãnh đạo nên cứ hỏi
this Buddhist. We respectfully request guidance from the Dharma center
phật tử kia thỉnh Cô chỉ dạy đạo tràng
on how to encourage others in both
nên sách tấn như thế nào với hai trường
the questioner and the person being asked.
hợp người đi hỏi và người được Hỏi như
Dear fellow practitioners,
trên ạ Cái Kính thưa các quý đạo hữu câu
this question comes from a Buddhist in the Golden Chrysanthemum
hỏi này là câu hỏi của phật tử trong câu
Club practicing the Six Harmonies.
lạc bộ Cúc Vàng tập tu Lục Hòa chúng ta
In our Golden Chrysanthemum Club practicing the Six Harmonies,
trong câu lạc bộ Cúc Vàng tập tu Lục Hòa
we have a rule for
Chúng ta có quy định
practicing the Six Harmonies
thực hành lục hòa theo đúng thứ lớp
according to the correct order. That is, matters concerning the group must be
theo đúng thứ lớp tức là việc ở tổ thì
asked of the group, matters concerning the
phải hỏi ở tổ
committee must be asked of the committee, and for certain
việc của ban thì hỏi ở ban
matters,
còn các việc nào đó quy định
after asking the group, the group asks the committee, and only then can we
sau khi hỏi Tổ rồi tổ hỏi lên ban rồi
answer. In other words, we have
mới trả lời tức là chúng ta có rất là
many...  The regulations, those rules, are hierarchical regulations. That is,
nhiều quy định quy định đó là quy định
respect for one another in a hierarchical order. That is the principle of the
trọng lẫn nhau đó là phép tắc của pháp
Six Harmonies, called the etiquette and rules of the
Lục Hòa đấy gọi là lễ nghi phép tắc của
Six Harmonies. It's similar to a
pháp Lục Hòa cũng giống như trong gia
family; in a family, there are
đình trong gia đình thì cũng có lễ nghi
etiquette and rules regarding hierarchy between grandparents, parents,
phép tắc trên dưới giữa ông bà cha mẹ
children, grandchildren,
con cái Cháu chắt đúng không
etc. In the Golden Chrysanthemum Club,
thì trong câu lạc bộ Cúc Vàng tập tu Lục
we also have hierarchical rules.
Hòa chúng ta cũng có phép tắc thứ lớp
It's an intellectual organization,
trên dưới nó là một tổ chức trí thức nó
similar to government agencies;
giống như là các tổ chức cơ quan nhà
it's also hierarchical. For example, when we
nước ấy nó cũng thứ lớp ví dụ Chúng ta
apply for a resume, we have to get the
đi xin sơ yếu lý lịch chúng ta phải xin
signature of the group leader, right? Then we send it to the
tổ chữ ký của tổ phải không gửi đến
ward. That's the hierarchy. Everything
phường Tức là nó thứ lớp tất cả việc gì
in society is also hierarchical. When
ở trong xã hội này nó cũng rất thứ lớp
we work for the government, it's the same: the group leader, the
chúng ta đi làm ở nhà nước cũng thế thì
department leader, the
việc của tổ của phòng của ban rồi đến
director, and then the general director,
mấy bến giám đốc rồi mới đến tổng công
right? That's the regulation, a
ty phải không Tức là quy định là một cái
rule belonging to the intellectual class, an
quy định thuộc của giới trí thức của tổ
organization arranged
chức được sắp xếp
to ensure smooth operation,
khiến cho vận hành được Hanh Thông
allowing people to live with respect and
khiến cho con người sống có tôn trọng có
order in society.
trật tự của xã hội phải không thì cái tổ
This Six Harmonies organization is such an organization.  This
chức lục Hòa này nó là cái tổ chức như
makes people live according to proper
vậy khiến cho người ta sống đúng lễ nghi
etiquette and respect for hierarchy, doesn't it, dear fellow
phép tắc trên dưới phải không các quý
practitioners? It makes work go smoothly,
đạo hữu khiến cho công việc được Hanh
hearts are respected, and
Thông tâm được tôn trọng nhau mọi việc
life is harmonious, right? That's
sống nó được Hòa Thuận đúng không Thế
why it's called the Six Harmonies. And
cho nên mới gọi là lục Hòa mà
in the Dharma community, we have
trong đạo tràng thì chúng ta có phân
clearly defined roles and responsibilities. When we
chức danh nhiệm vụ rõ ràng khi chúng ta
have a role and a responsibility,
có chức danh chúng ta có nhiệm vụ thì
we must fulfill
chúng ta phải có bổn phận hoàn thành cái
that responsibility.
nhiệm vụ đó
For example, what does the Dharma community leader do? What does the
Cái nhiệm vụ ví dụ đạo tràng trưởng là
transportation committee leader do?
phải làm gì phải không trưởng ban xe
What does the administration committee leader do?
phải làm gì trưởng ban tri sự làm gì Ban
What does the ceremonial committee leader do? Those roles are linked
nghi lễ làm gì chức danh đó nó gắn liền
to our responsibilities of caring for each other. We are
với bổn phận lo cho nhau chúng ta chẳng
simply caring for each other within the Dharma community;
qua chỉ là lo cho nhau trong đạo tràng
we are not caring for anyone else,
thôi chứ chúng ta chả phải lo cho ai cả
right? Each person has their own role, just like
phải không Mỗi người mỗi việc cũng như
in a house where parents go to work, children stay
trong nhà cha mẹ thì đi làm phải không
home to cook, sweep, clean, and
con cái thì phải ở nhà nấu cơm
go to school.
quét nhà dọn nhà đi học mỗi người mỗi
Each person has their own responsibility, making the family peaceful. Everyone is happy, everyone
Mỗi người đều được hạnh phúc mỗi người
is satisfied. In the Dharma community,
đều được thỏa mãn thì ở trong đạo tràng
we don't serve anyone outside the
chúng ta cũng không phục vụ ai ngoài đạo
community; we only serve ourselves, right? We
tràng cả chỉ phục vụ chúng ta thôi phải
only serve ourselves.
không phục vụ cho chúng ta thôi thì
We must have such a hierarchy so that the
chúng ta phải có thứ lớp như thế thì sự
service is complete, well-ordered, and follows the
phục vụ nó mới được đầy đủ và nó được
rules. And here
nó được đúng quy tắc thế và ở đây thì
today, the Mind-Viewing Enlightenment says to you, esteemed
hôm nay tâm chiếu Hoàn quán nói cho các
Dharma friends, that the Mind-Viewing Enlightenment does
quý Đạo Hữu này tâm chiếu Hoàn quán
nothing but cultivate Bodhicitta. You
không làm việc gì ngoài Tâm Bồ Đề
have read in the sutra that
các quý Đạo Hữu đã đọc trong bài kinh mà
the Buddha taught seven principles that prevent a country from
Đức Phật dạy bảy pháp khiến đất nước
being destroyed. One of these principles is respect and reverence between
không bị diệt vong trong đấy có một Pháp
young and old, superior and inferior, and upholding
trẻ già trên dưới kính nhường giữ gìn lễ
etiquette and rules. This is a cause that
nghi phép tắc đấy là một nhân duyên
makes the country stable, preventing enemies from
khiến cho đất nước được bền vững kẻ thù
invading or conquering it, and
không thể xâm hại cũng không ai xâm
preventing its downfall.
chiếm đất nước được mà đất nước không bị
That is, talented leaders will emerge in the country, and we will live a good life. The Mind-Viewing Enlightenment has encouraged you, esteemed
đề này tâm chiếu Hoàn quán đã sách tấn
Dharma friends, many times. Therefore, the
các quý đạo hữu nhiều rồi cho nên pháp
Six Harmonies bring happiness to ourselves and
Lục Hòa mang lại hạnh phúc cho mình mang
happiness to the world, right?
lại hạnh phúc cho thế gian phải không
Because the Six Harmonies have merit, they help
Tại vì pháp luật hòa là có công đức
us become Buddhas, and the
khiến chúng ta làm phật mà
merit of becoming a Buddha
đã công đức làm Phật thì công đức đấy
benefits the world. Therefore, practicing the Six
làm lợi thế gian cho nên thực hành Lục
Harmonies allows us to achieve both our respectful hearts and a
Hòa vừa được cái tâm tôn kính của mình
beautiful hierarchy,
thành tựu vừa được thứ lớp trên dưới đẹp
right? Joyful and happy.  We have
đẽ phải không vui vẻ hoan hỷ vừa có một
another paramita (perfection) of merit: making the
cái nhân duyên ba-la-mật nữa là làm cho
country better.
đất nước được tốt đẹp mỗi mỗi người ở
Each of us
trong chúng ta cũng thế thôi Ai ai cũng
wants to live in a good country,
muốn mình sống trong một đất nước tốt
but that country is
thì đất nước nào đâu là do mỗi con người
built by each and every one of us. It's
của chúng ta xây dựng lên là trách nhiệm
everyone's responsibility, is
của mỗi người
n't it? We often blame
phải không Mình cứ trách rằng đất nước
our country for not being good enough, thinking that we
mình không tốt là do mỗi con người của
ourselves aren't good enough to make it better.
mình chưa đủ tốt để làm cho đất nước tốt
Isn't that right, fellow practitioners? If each
có đúng không các đạo hữu Thế nếu mỗi
of us is aware that we are
người chúng ta đều ý thức là chúng ta là
members of this country,
một thành viên của đất nước này là một
citizens of this country, and we all work
công dân của đất nước này chúng ta đều
together to make it better, then the
chung tay làm cho đất nước này tốt đẹp
country will be good. And we Buddhists
nước sẽ tốt đẹp thôi và phật tử chúng ta
must do that. That's what the Buddha
phải làm điều đó Đó là điều mà Đức Phật
taught us: we must repay the Four Great Debts of Gratitude.
dạy chúng ta là phải báo Tứ Trọng Ân
As disciples of the Buddha, we must know and be grateful to our
là người đệ tử Phật phải biết phải biết
country. What is gratitude to the country? Gratitude to
biết ơn đất nước mà Ân đất nước là gì Ân
previous generations? And we must truly be
những thế hệ đi trước và phải thực sự là
those who contribute to making the country
những người đóng góp khiến cho đất nước
better, right? So, besides
tốt đẹp có đúng không Thế thì ngoài cái
cultivating our morality
việc chúng ta tu sửa đạo đức
daily, we should do charity work.
hàng ngày chúng ta đi làm từ thiện Chúng
We know how to live.  Loving, knowing how to let go,
Ta Biết Sống yêu thương biết buông bỏ
living with filial piety—these are
sống biết Hiếu Thuận khiến trong gia
meaningful qualities within our families, contributing to the well-being of each
đình nhà mình có nghĩa để cho mỗi thành
member and each element of the nation. A
viên mỗi yếu tố
beautiful family, where everyone is conscious of creating a
đình mình tốt đẹp ai cũng có ý thức làm
beautiful family, leads to a beautiful nation.
gia đình tốt đẹp thì đất nước tốt đẹp
We must cultivate
mình phải tập sống đúng bổn phận của
our responsibilities; if we have that habit,
mình mình có thói quen đấy thì trong gia
we will also live according to that habit within our families.
đình mình mình cũng sẽ sống đúng thói
Isn't that true? Because when
quen đấy Có đúng là ít không Bởi vì khi
we live according to our responsibilities,
mình sống đúng bổn phận của mình rồi thì
we won't do anything that goes against them. We wo
mình làm những cái gì trái bổn phận của
n't do it because we've learned this and
mình không làm vì mình tập cái này rồi
that. For example, a person
cái kia mình không làm ví dụ một người
who lives a life full of etiquette and manners,
mà sống đầy đủ lễ nghi phép tắc được rèn
cultivated in this way, will treat everyone
giũa như vậy thì trên dưới họ đối xử rất
well: grandparents as grandparents, parents as parents, spouses as
là tốt ông bà ra ông bà cha mẹ ra cha mẹ
spouses, children as
vợ ra vợ chồng ra chồng con cái ra con
children. But those who
cái nhưng mà những người như thế này
don't understand etiquette and manners,
không hiểu gì lễ nghi phép tắc thì làm
how can they do that? They won't bring
sao họ làm được không mang đến được cho
happiness to their families or contribute
gia đình hạnh phúc không mang đến được
to a better country. We keep saying
cho đất nước tốt đẹp mà chúng ta cứ bảo
we love our children and grandchildren, we love our great-grandchildren,
chúng ta yêu con yêu cháu chúng ta yêu
but we must leave
cháu chắt chúng ta thì chúng ta phải để
something behind for them, right?
lại cho nó cái gì chứ phải không Đấy
This belongs to the Bodhi Mind. This thought belongs to the
Thuộc Về Tâm Bồ Đề suy nghĩ này thuộc về
Bodhi Mind, this thought
suy nghĩ thuộc tâm bồ đề suy nghĩ này
belongs to the Paramitas. Dear fellow practitioners, the
thuộc về ba la mật các quý đạo hữu công
merits we create here belong to the Paramitas.
đức chúng ta làm ra đây là thuộc
We aspire to
ba-la-mật chúng ta mong muốn chúng ta
live in harmony with the Six Harmonies. We pray for
sống thứ lớp Lục Hòa trên chúng ta cầu
Buddhahood, bringing prosperity to the country. By
thành Phật mang lại cho đất nước tốt đẹp
living in harmony,
và chúng ta sống Lục Hòa như thế là
we have created two karmic connections that
chúng ta đã có hai nhân duyên trong bệnh
prevent the country from
nhân duyên khiến đất nước không bị diệt
perishing. Isn't that a great benefit? The
vong lợi ích có lớn không phải không Đức
Buddha taught that if the people of
Phật dạy rằng là nếu nhân dân đất nước
that country lived according to just one karmic connection, the
đấy chỉ cần sống một một cái duyên thôi
country would not perish.
thì đất nước đã không bị diệt vong rồi
Let alone seven connections, we,
chứ đừng nói đến bảy duyên
as disciples of the Buddha, live according to
là người đệ tử Phật chúng ta sống được
many karmic connections. We practice filial piety towards our
rất nhiều cái duyên đó tập Hiếu kính cha
parents, right? With unity of heart and mind, the
mẹ đúng không
king wants to make
trên dưới một lòng mới lại vua muốn cho
this country prosperous, isn't that unity of
đất nước này tốt đẹp lên có phải trên
heart and mind? Then we, the
dưới một lòng không thế rồi chúng ta thì
old and young in the Dharma hall, in the
Già trẻ ở trong đạo tràng ở trong gia
family, with proper conduct and etiquette, fulfill our duties.
đình trên dưới lễ nghi phép tắc làm đúng
That creates so many karmic connections.
bổn phận thế là được bao nhân duyên rồi
Fourth, let's cultivate morality
thứ tư là hay cùng nhau tu sửa đạo đức
together, discuss and cultivate morality.
cùng bàn luận tu sửa đạo đức đây chúng
We are sitting here cultivating morality.
ta đang ngồi đây là tu sửa đạo đức đây
This question is: Are you, fellow practitioners,
trong cái câu hỏi này là các quý đạo hữu
not living according to moral principles and respecting others?
sống chưa đúng với đạo đức Tôn trọng
People have their duties, and you are interfering with yours.
phải không Người ta có bổn phận của
That
người ta mình làm tranh bổn phận ta Đấy
is disrespect. That is stealing,
là không tôn trọng Đấy là ăn cắp
stealing reputation, isn't it? That is violating the
ăn cắp danh có đúng không Đấy là phạm
precepts;
giới
you are not allowed to guide those who
mình không được phép đi hướng dẫn người
have not been assigned to do so.
chưa được phân công mà mình đi hướng dẫn
That is stealing reputation and spiritual energy. As you
đấy là trộm danh đạo khí các quý Đạo Hữu
know, in the Ksitigarbha Sutra,
đã biết là trong kinh từ bi Địa Tạng bảo
the sin of stealing reputation and spiritual energy leads to death
xám cái tội trộm danh đạo khí chết đi
and falling into hell, with your feet hanging down and your
rồi rơi xuống địa ngục chân thì treo lên
head down. You
đầu thì chồng xuống dưới mà đọc kinh
must remember the sutras; if your mind is not yet at peace, you may remember
phải nhớ kinh chứ tâm chưa quán thì nhớ
less, but remember what is necessary. This is
ít nhưng mà nhớ những cái cần nhớ Đây
not normal. It is
không phải chuyện bình thường đâu Nó là
breaking harmony, meaning not practicing
phá hòa hợp Tức là không thực hành hòa
harmony, not practicing the Six Harmonies. Secondly, it is
hợp không thực hành Lục Hòa thứ hai gọi
theft. Thirdly, it is not sowing
là trộm cắp thứ ba là không gieo được
any good karma for yourself, your
một tí nhân nhân quả tốt đẹp nào cho
country, your family,
mình cho đất nước cả cho gia đình và xã
society, and yourself, right? And for those
hội và bản thân đúng không Thế còn người
who uphold the Six Harmonies and diligently study like this,
mà giữ được Lục Hòa chăm học như thế này
we benefit; we
thì chúng ta đã được lợi ích về chúng ta
adorn our bodies,
trang nghiêm được cái thân của mình
adorn our
trang nghiêm được tâm của mình tăng
minds, and increase our respect, right? So,
trưởng được cái tâm tôn trọng lên phải
we know how to live in order.  So, when
Thế Chúng Ta Biết Sống thứ lớp thì chúng
we go home or to any place in society,
ta về gia đình hay đi đến đâu xã hội
we know how to behave correctly, right?
chúng ta biết ứng xử có đúng không Chúng
We're not causing trouble. This is causing trouble in the
ta không gây rối đâu Đây là đang gây rối
Dharma hall, isn't it?
đạo tràng đấy chứ Có đúng không Chúng ta
Wherever we are, we live like this, so is
ở đâu chúng ta cũng sống thế này thì có
n't that causing trouble? If we cause trouble,
phải gây rối lên không gây rối lên rồi
we'll even cause the country's
chúng ta lại còn làm cho đất nước bị
destruction, won't we? If we cause trouble, it
diệt vong phải không chúng ta gây rối
will be karma,
này thì là nhân quả khiến đất tức bị
causing the country's destruction. If these seven principles prevent the country from being
bảy pháp này khiến đất nước không bị
destroyed, then doing the
diệt vong thế thì 7 thì cái làm ngược
opposite will cause the country's destruction. Do you
lại thì đất nước sẽ bị diệt vong thôi Nó
see, dear fellow practitioners? Practicing in the
các quý đạo hữu thấy không tu trong pháp
Six Harmonies is our blessing, is
Lục Hòa này là phúc báo của mình
n't it? It's our blessing to be able to
các bạn phải không là phúc của mình mình
practice like this
được tu như này trong phạm là phúc báo
within the Dharma
của mình thì mình được tu trong đạo
hall. We create so much merit, so
tràng Mình mới tạo ra nhiều công đức như
much blessings, and we can be more dignified.
nhiều Phước báo và mình mới Trang Nghiêm
Therefore, dear fellow practitioners, you
được mình lên nhé Cho nên là các quý đạo
must be self-aware. This is the self-aware part, but
hữu phải tự giác Đây là phần tự giác còn
the part about the mind-viewing and perfect contemplation is
tâm chiếu Hoàn quán xin nói ra cái phần
mandatory. It's a rule of
là nó bắt buộc đó là quy định của câu
our Golden Chrysanthemum Club that we must
lạc bộ cúc vàng của chúng ta là phải tập
practice the Six Harmonies, meaning we must practice
tu Lục Hòa tức là chúng ta phải tập tu
the Six Harmonies of our Buddha.
các pháp Lục Hòa của Phật chúng ta tự
This is a voluntary organization. We voluntarily
nguyện Đây là một tổ chức có tự nguyện
practice the Six Harmonious Principles of Righteousness;
tự nguyện Hành Thiện theo sáu Pháp Hòa
no one
Kính Lục Hòa chúng ta tự nguyện không ai
forces us to do so. We practice the
bắt buộc phải không tự nguyện thực hành
Buddha's teachings voluntarily, and everything we practice
pháp Phật thế và thực hành cái gì nó
has its rules. Therefore,
cũng phải có quy tắc của nó Cho nên để ở
here we are referring to the Six Harmonious Principles. So, if any of you
đây là quy tắc Lục Hòa Thế thì các quý
have
đạo hữu nào mà đã
violated these Six Harmonious Principles, you should sincerely repent. The Mind-
vi phạm vào cái quy tắc Lục Hòa này rồi
Illuminating Enlightenment Club will guide you on
bộ tâm chiếu Hoàn quán sẽ hướng dẫn cho
how to repent. First,
biết cách sám hối nhé đầu tiên là chúng
we will have a public repentance ceremony at the Dharma Hall
ta sẽ phát nổ ở đạo tràng chúng ta sám
and post it on the club's website
hối rồi đăng lên câu lạc bộ để các cái
so that we can repent and eliminate our
để chúng ta Sám hối cho tiêu tiêu nỗi
sins. Furthermore,
tiêu tội Thế còn lại về phía đạo tràng
if we see any Buddhists behaving in this way, we must
thì nếu thấy các phật tử nào như thế này
immediately remind them.
thì phải nhắc nhở ngay
If they do not learn from their mistakes, we must hold a
nếu như mà nhắc nhở không rút kinh
meeting.
nghiệm thì phải họp bàn vào họp vào thế
And here,
và ở đây thì cái những cái tiêu chuẩn
we must lower the standards to the level of
này chúng ta phải xuống thành phần xuống
Buddhists; that is, those who are
thành phần phật tử tức là đang là phật
officially practicing the Six Harmonious Principles must be made to remain in the Bodhisattva stage,
tử chính thức tu Lục Hòa thì chúng ta
not yet having made the Bodhi vow, to practice the
phải xuống giữ thính chưa phát nguyện Bồ
Six Harmonious Principles. They must make the Bodhi vow
Đề tu Lục Hòa để phải phát nguyện Bồ Đề
and practice the Six Harmonious Principles again.  Report
Tu là hòa lại và phải thông báo cái việc
this matter to the Dharma community and inform the
này với đạo tràng và phải bạch lên trên
club about it. So, all of
câu lạc bộ việc này nhé Thế thì tất cả
us in the Dharma community, as
đạo tràng chúng ta cùng như thế đã là
Buddhists in the Golden Chrysanthemum Club practicing the Six Harmonies,
phật tử trong câu lạc bộ Cúc Vàng tập tu
must at least bring
Lục Hòa tối thiểu mình phải mang lại
goodness to ourselves, meaning we must develop our
Thiện cho mình tức là phải phát triển
morality.
đạo đức
Do you understand, dear fellow practitioners? Secondly,
các quý đạo hữu rõ chưa ạ việc thứ hai
cultivating body and mind in this way
là rèn giũa thân tâm như vậy đạo đức như
will bring happiness to
vậy mình sẽ mang lại hạnh phúc trong gia
our families. We will be role models in our families and in
đình mình là mình sẽ là người làm tấm
society.
gương trong gia đình rộng ra đến xã hội
Furthermore, we will practice the
và nữa là chúng ta sẽ thực hành các pháp
Paramitas, leading to
ba-la-mật khiến cho đất nước được hòa
lasting peace in the country, producing talented individuals to
bình bền vững phát sinh những nhân tài
lead the nation, and ensuring that our children and grandchildren do not suffer hardship.
mà lãnh đạo đất nước phải không khiến
And even if we are
lầm than khổ sở Và thậm chí mình là
good people, our children and grandchildren will also be good people, right? If we are good and
người tốt đẹp thì con cháu mình cũng tốt
live
đẹp mà phải không mình tốt đẹp mình sống
morally, we have blessings, and our children and grandchildren will
đạo đức mình có phước báo thì con cháu
also benefit from those blessings. If we have
mình nó cũng được hưởng phước mình có
blessings, those who are blessed will be born
phước thì những người có phước được sinh
into our family as our grandchildren and help us. If we
về nhà mình làm cháu mình làm chắc mình
have blessings, our children, even if they are
rồi mình có phước thì con cái mình đang
not good, will become good to serve
không tốt phải trở nên tốt để phục vụ
us and repay our kindness. If we are not good,
mình để báo hiếu mình mình không tốt thì
our children...  It won't change cause and
con cái mình nó sẽ không thay đổi nhân
effect, it won't be good, so it will lose
quả nó sẽ không tốt cho nên nó mất đi
its benefits. Right, fellow
lợi ích của mình thôi phải các quý đạo
practitioners? Think broadly, this is much
hữu rồi các quý đạo hữu tư duy rộng ra
broader. It still brings
cái này nó còn rộng lắm Nó còn được lợi
many benefits. Conversely, if
ích nhiều lắm cơ Thế thì ngược lại chúng
we don't practice correctly,
ta không được thành đúng được khoa thì
we are creating mistakes. Making mistakes will lead to the
chúng ta đang tạo lỗi tạo lỗi thì nó sẽ
opposite, right, fellow
bị cái ngược lại như thế kia phải không
practitioners? It's not good. It wo
các đạo hữu ngược lại nó không tốt Nó
n't make this country beautiful, it won't
không làm cho đất nước này tươi đẹp
make our families beautiful, and it won't
không làm cho gia đình tươi đẹp và không
make us happy in
làm cho mình hạnh phúc ngay trong hiện
this life and in many future lives. We will certainly
tại và đến nhiều kiếp sau chắc chắn là
suffer if we don't
phải khổ đau rồi nếu chúng ta không thực
practice harmony correctly and instead disrupt it like this,
hành đúng được hòa mà đi phá như thế này
right? So, after hearing
phải không cho nên sau khi nghe cái câu
this answer, all fellow practitioners and the leadership of the
trả lời này thì tất cả các đạo hữu ban
Dharma center must meet and see which of
cán sự đạo tràng phải họp vào xem tất cả
our Buddhists are still violating
các phật tử của mình ai còn vi phạm Cái
this. This must be resolved immediately according to the
này ngay lập tức giải quyết theo đúng
Six Harmonies regulations. Otherwise,
quy định Lục Hòa nếu không thì bản thân
we ourselves won't be fulfilling our duties, and neither will
chúng ta cũng không làm đúng bổn phận
the leadership and the management.
đâu ban lãnh đạo ban cán sự cũng không
If we let it continue like this...
làm đúng bổn phận đâu Nếu để như thế này
Therefore, the mind at the temple has made
nhé Cho nên tâm chiếu ở quán đã phát
this vow:
nguyện thế này
practice for quality, not...  We're taking a number of
tu lấy chất lượng chứ không lấy số đối
people who want to practice the Six Harmonies Dharma, so let's practice
tượng ai muốn tu pháp Lục Hòa thì vào tu
together, encourage each other, and
với mình cùng nhau tu sách tấn nhau trợ
support each other in our practice. One person
duyên cho nhau tu vì một mình thì không
cannot practice the Six Harmonies Dharma alone; it requires a community.
thể tu Lục Hòa được phải có đại chúng
We don't need numbers,
thế còn chúng ta không cần số lượng cho
so we don't need those who are stubborn and unwilling to learn from their mistakes, right?
nên không cần những người bảo thủ không
Although
rút kinh nghiệm phải không Tuy rằng
we are practitioners
chúng ta là người đang tu có lúc có lỗi
and sometimes make mistakes, we must acknowledge them.
nhưng có lỗi thì phải biết nhận lỗi
When pointed out, we must learn from our mistakes and
khi được chỉ lỗi thì phải rút kinh
correct them. We can't just keep doing the same thing.
nghiệm phải sửa đổi chứ không thể nào mà
Therefore, those who are like that,
nên những ai mà như thế thì thôi chúng
we'll let them go. If they're not happy,
ta cho xuống thành phần Nếu họ không
then they can leave the club and practice on their own. They won't practice in the
thì thì họ tự tu thôi Không tu trong câu
club anymore. So, our
lạc bộ nữa Có gì đâu cho nên là chúng ta
spirit is to
với tinh thần là với tinh thần là trước
prioritize ourselves first,
lo độ mình sau mới lo độ người
then others. When we help people practice Buddhism, we must practice correctly. If we help them but they do it wrong, then we don't help them or ourselves. Furthermore, since we've vowed to practice the Six Harmonies Dharma, helping
nguyện tu Lục Hòa rồi thì mình đi giúp
others to practice the
người là giúp người tu Lục Hòa
Six Harmonies Dharma allows us to practice as well.  The Six
thì mình giúp người tu Lục Hòa thì mình
Harmonies (Lục Hòa) brings blessings,
được tu Lục Hòa thì mình được phước báo
so first, it helps us, and
cho nên là trước thì nó độ gì độ mình
we must know that our actions are right.
mình phải biết việc làm của mình đúng đã
We cannot allow
chứ mình không thể nào lại để cho người
others to not practice the Six Harmonies within the Dharma; that would be
ta không tu Lục Hòa ở trong pháp Lục Hòa
failing
được thì như thế là mình không làm đúng
our duty. How can we say, "
bổn phận của mình thế thì làm sao gọi là
First, help yourself, then help others"? We
trước lo độ mình sau lo độ người mình
must fulfill our duty first, and only then
phải làm đúng bổn phận của mình rồi mình
can we benefit others.
mới làm lợi cho người khác được chứ Đấy
That means, "First, help yourself, then help sentient beings." It's not selfishness. It means that only when
của nó là gì không phải ích kỷ Tức là
we follow the Dharma can we
mình có đúng pháp thì mình mới làm lợi
benefit sentient beings and others. If
ích được cho chúng sinh cho người khác
we don't follow the Dharma, we will cause
mình không đúng pháp thì mình sẽ làm cho
others to do the wrong thing. It's
người khác không đúng pháp chứ không
not selfishness. This saying, this
phải là ích kỷ đâu nhé cái câu nói này
teaching, is from the
cái câu mà dạy là của đức Phật lời dạy
Buddha. It's not
của đức Phật Nó không phải là như chúng
simply what we think: "So, practicing
ta suy nghĩ đơn thuần là ơ Thế Tu Đạo
Buddhism means first helping yourself, then helping
Phật là trước lo độ mình sau mới độ
sentient beings, and that's selfishness."
chúng sinh thì như vậy là ích kỷ à
No, it means that it helps us first. It means we
không phải trước nó độ mình tức là mình
must be enlightened and practice correctly.
phải giác ngộ mình phải thực hành đúng
From our enlightenment and correct practice,
thì từ cái việc giác ngộ thực hành đúng
we can then help sentient beings to be
của mình thì mình mới khiến cho chúng
enlightened and do the right thing.
sinh được giác ngộ được đúng được
I never think about whether
chứ còn nếu mình luôn luôn không nghĩ là
my actions will bring
việc làm này của mình có đem lại kết quả
good results for me or not; I'm only
tốt đẹp cho mình hay không thì mình chỉ
harming sentient beings. Isn't that right? For
làm hại chúng sinh thôi Có đúng không Ví
example, if I'm angry at someone and
dụ như là mình nói mình tức người này
I curse them, cursing
mình chửi người ta chẳng hạn thế Thì cái
them doesn't
việc mà chửi người ta thế này thì không
benefit me. If I see that,
làm lợi cho mình rồi thì mình thấy thế
I won't curse them, and that's how I
mình sẽ không chửi người ta thế là mình
benefit them, right? So, in practicing
làm lợi cho người ta có đúng không cho
Buddhism, before doing anything, you
nên là tu Phật trước tất cả các việc thì
must know that the action will bring
phải biết việc làm đó mang đến cái Phước
you good karma. Only then should you
quả cho mình tốt đẹp rồi mình mới được
do it. If the action doesn't
làm Còn nếu cái việc làm đó Không mang
bring you good karma, then you shouldn't do it.
đến tốt đẹp cho mình thì mình không làm
And here, the guidance of the Mind-
và ở đây lời hướng dẫn của tâm chiếu
Viewing and the club's regulations are the same:
Hoàn quán và các quy định của câu lạc bộ
first, it must
cũng thế là đầu tiên phải mang lại lợi
benefit you. This is the Six Harmonious Principles.
ích cho mình đã đây Đúng Pháp Lục Hòa đã
The Mind-Viewing and the reprimanding of fellow
và tâm chiếu Hoàn quán có khiển trách
practitioners who don't practice correctly is a
các quý Đạo Hữu không thực hành đúng là
correct reprimand to help them
khiển trách đúng khiển trách để cho các
progress.
quý đạo hữu tiến bộ và cái sự khiển
This reprimand is a reminder, and
trách này chính là cái sự nhắc nhở và
this reminder benefits the
đây cái sự nhắc nhở này đem lại lợi ích
Mind-Viewing and the practice. What is the benefit? It is that in
cho tâm trương quán cái lợi ích là gì Là
the future, the Mind-Viewing and the practice will
sau này tâm chiếu Hoàn quán có tu tập sẽ
always...  We always encounter supportive people and
luôn luôn gặp được người trợ duyên sách
masters who help us cultivate the
tấn được những bậc thầy giúp cho mình tu
Path, right? That's the benefit; we must first
Tiến Đạo phải không Đấy lợi trước phải
consider our own benefit before we even think about it. If we
lo đến lợi đi cho mình sau mới đi nhắc
remind others
chứ phải không chị đi nhắc mà lại lại
without considering what
không nghĩ là mình cái việc nhắc nhở này
we gain from this, then what's the point of reminding them?
của mình mình được cái gì thì đi nhắc
The esteemed fellow practitioners in the
làm gì thế thì các quý đạo hữu trong ban
leadership committee should also consider the
cán sự cũng thế cũng phải giống một cái
benefit, just like the mind of this practitioner. When
lợi giống như tâm chiếu ông quán này
we help others
cũng phải mình đi giúp cho người thực
practice the Dharma correctly, what benefit do we gain
hành đúng pháp thì mình được lợi gì sau
later? We get to practice the Dharma correctly, receive
này mình được thực hành đúng pháp được
support from others, and have masters to
mọi người trợ duyên cho mình có bậc thầy
guide us in practicing the Dharma correctly.
dẫn dắt cho mình thực hành đúng pháp cho
So we must help others practice the
nên mình phải giúp đỡ người thực hành
Dharma correctly. Isn't that the same as first helping
đúng pháp Thế có phải là trước lo độ
ourselves, then helping sentient beings?
mình sau mới độ chúng sinh không nhé Cho
Therefore, the mind of this practitioner hopes that
nên là tâm chiếu Hoàn quán mong rằng câu
every Dharma center in our club is a
lạc bộ của chúng ta đạo tràng nào cũng
true Dharma center,
là đạo tràng thật
not just
không phải là những không phải chúng ta
a group of
tập trung vào đây để trở thành một đám
aimless, idle people. Isn't that right, esteemed fellow
người không có mục đích
practitioners? It's
các quý đạo hữu
not just for
không phải là vì vì
fun; we practice to seek
vui mà Mà Đi tu mà phải tầm cầu hạnh
happiness for ourselves in this life and the next, bringing
phúc cho mình đời này đời sau mang đến
happiness to our families in this life.
hạnh phúc cho gia đình ngay đời này
Bringing happiness to all beings in society
mang đến hạnh phúc cho chúng sinh xã hội
right now, through our present actions,
ngay bây giờ ngay hành động hiện tại của
isn't that right, fellow practitioners? We must do
mình có phải không các đạo hữu phải như
that, and bring lasting happiness to the majority. That's how we must do it.
thế và mang hạnh phúc kéo dài cho số
Mindfulness and mindfulness also wish all fellow
nhé tâm chiếu Hoàn quán cũng chúc các
practitioners diligence and that we always
quý đạo hữu tinh tấn và chúng ta luôn
practice the Six Harmonies correctly,
thực hành đúng pháp Lục Hòa làm lợi ích
benefiting ourselves and the majority,
cho mình và làm lợi ích cho số đông theo
according to the Buddha's teachings, not betraying the efforts of the Buddhas,
đúng lời Đức Phật dạy không phụ công chư
Bodhisattvas, and holy monks, not betraying the teachings of our
phật bồ tát thánh tăng không phụ công
teachers and masters.
Thầy Tổ dạy dỗ nhé
[Music]
[âm nhạc]